<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 19, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00129701</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NHLICX3510</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00129701</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Can We Reduce Hospital Attendance Without Compromising Care by the Use of Telephone Consultation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Proposal to Study Whether We Can Reduce Hospital Attendance by Those With Respiratory Conditions Without Compromising Care by the Use of Telephone Consultation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Imperial College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Imperial College London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Consultation time in busy respiratory clinics is inevitably limited and attendance is often
      disruptive to patients’ lives; involves time, expense, travel, and waiting; and can have
      effects upon occupation. Published work suggests that patient satisfaction with telephone
      consultations is high and this subject has recently been extensively reviewed by one of the
      study investigators. In respiratory medicine there is United States (US) data to suggest
      that the regular telephoning of adolescents with asthma by a specialist nurse can reduce
      unscheduled use of health service resources. In the United Kingdom (UK), a randomised,
      controlled trial in primary care has shown that, compared to face to face consultations, use
      of the telephone can enable greater numbers of patients with asthma to be reviewed. Another
      of the study investigators has undertaken a feasibility study in a general respiratory
      clinic and has shown the concept of alternating face to face consultation with telephone
      consultation to be acceptable to over 80% of patients. Over one third were assessed to be
      suitable in that they did not need to attend the clinic for either physical examination or
      for investigations. It is therefore proposed to evaluate the feasibility, acceptability,
      time savings and safety of the use of telephone consultation in 3 respiratory clinics in the
      Department of Respiratory Medicine at Charing Cross Hospital.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients to be included in the study would be those attending 3 respiratory clinics. The
      patients would be asked if they were willing to have a telephone consultation instead of
      their next face to face consultation and this would be explained to them.

      “Many patients attending a Chest Clinic need to do so only once.  For others their condition
      merits regular review. Most of these people need to come to the clinic because they need
      chest x-rays, blood tests or breathing tests.  However some patients return for review of
      their condition without needing any specialist investigations.  We are keen to assess what
      proportion of our patients would be suitable for telephone consultations rather than face to
      face consultations and to see what advantages there might be for both patients and doctors.
      We are therefore interested to assess the use of telephone consultation where suitable and
      would like to know if you would be willing to try telephone consultation for your next
      appointment. In the case of telephone consultation you would be offered a day, date and time
      at which you would be phoned.  Your consultant, would then ring you him or herself within
      half an hour of the appointed time {and procedurally it has been agreed by the trial
      participants that if, for any reason, during the trial period they are delayed with the
      previous patient they will excuse themselves to telephone the following  patient to say that
      they have been delayed and they will ring them back within 15 minutes, for example}  and
      with your clinical notes in front of them he or she would  enquire in the usual way
      regarding how you feel, ask about your symptoms and give advice regarding any concerns you
      may have or advise regarding changes in treatment. You would subsequently receive a copy of
      the letter summarising the telephone consultation when it was sent to your general
      practitioner.  If the telephone consultation suggested that you needed to be seen in the
      clinic you would be offered an appointment within two weeks of the telephone call.”

      Demographic details and disease diagnosis would be recorded, for those not deemed suitable
      or for those not wishing to take part and they would continue to attend traditional face to
      face consultations. Those having a telephone consultation would subsequently revert to
      traditional consultation pending results of the trial. Frequency of planned consultation
      would be as per the consultant's usual practice.

      Procedurally, it was agreed that for those patients agreeing to have their next consultation
      by telephone, the doctor would check the phone number which they wished for the
      investigators to use and this would be inserted in the notes at the end of the previous
      consultation with a large black box around it, so that it could easily be spotted at the
      time of the telephone consultation.

      For all patients the following observations would be made: length of the telephone
      consultation, fail to be available when telephoned rate, and length of each face to face
      consultation.

      For each face to face consultation the following information would be recorded: the time
      they left home; time of arrival at hospital, time spent waiting for consultation, expense of
      attendance, both travel costs but also any indirect costs such as babysitting charges and
      loss of earnings.  For each telephone consultation the number of patients having to be
      reviewed within the next 2 weeks of the telephone consultation would be recorded, whether
      such expedited follow up was at the patient's or the doctor's behest.

      After both the telephone consultation and their subsequent face to face consultation the
      patients would be asked to complete the post consultation patient satisfaction
      questionnaire, the MISS 21 questionnaire and the Howie Enablement Instrument. Patients would
      be posted these scales by first class post on the day of a telephone consultation and handed
      them for completion after a face to face consultation and on each occasion they would be
      given a stamped addressed envelope in which to return the completed scores.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date>January 2006</completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Educational/Counseling/Training</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of those telephoned needing expedited follow up</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient costs associated with traditional face to face consultation</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Any differences between diseases</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment>500</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <condition>COPD</condition>
  <condition>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</condition>
  <condition>Interstitial Lung Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Bronchiectasis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Telephone consultation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who had already attended a respiratory clinic on at least two occasions and
             in whom it was perceived that there was a need for continued follow up in a hospital
             clinic with review needed more often than once per year

          -  Patients with no need for physical examinations or investigations such as chest
             X-rays, blood tests or lung function tests at every attendance

          -  Patients who had access to a confidential telephone line

          -  Patients who had no mental, hearing or linguistic problems
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Martyn R Partridge, MD FRCP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NHLI Imperial College</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NHLI Imperial College</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>W6 8RF</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pal B. Following up outpatients by telephone: pilot study. BMJ. 1998 May 30;316(7145):1647. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>9603747</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Car J, Sheikh A. Telephone consultations. BMJ. 2003 May 3;326(7396):966-9. Review. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>12727771</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Greineder DK, Loane KC, Parks P. Reduction in resource utilization by an asthma outreach program. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med. 1995 Apr;149(4):415-20.</citation>
    <PMID>7704170</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pinnock H, Bawden R, Proctor S, Wolfe S, Scullion J, Price D, Sheikh A. Accessibility, acceptability, and effectiveness in primary care of routine telephone review of asthma: pragmatic, randomised controlled trial. BMJ. 2003 Mar 1;326(7387):477-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12609944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Partridge MR. An assessment of the feasibility of telephone and email consultation in a chest clinic. Patient Educ Couns. 2004 Jul;54(1):11-3.</citation>
    <PMID>15210254</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2005</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 15, 2006</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 11, 2005</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bronchiectasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases, Interstitial</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
