<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 19, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01502709</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CVS-TMD-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01502709</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neurostimulation in Temporomandibular Disorders (TMD) Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>CVS</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomized Blinded Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trial of Caloric Vestibular Neurostimulation in Patients With Chronic TMD</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators propose to conduct a randomized blinded placebo-controlled clinical trial
      in patients with chronic TMD (N=20). Patients will be randomly assigned to receive either
      active treatment (caloric vestibular neurostimulation) or placebo for 3 visits. Data will be
      collected prior to and after treatment on thermal and mechanical pain thresholds, clinical
      signs and symptoms of TMD, and any adverse events.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Temporomandibular disorders (TMD) are musculoskeletal pain conditions characterized by pain
      in the temporomandibular joint and/or the masticatory muscles.  TMD are amongst the most
      common chronic musculoskeletal conditions affecting 6 to 12% of the general population yet
      there are no medicines approved specifically for its treatment. TMD cause substantial
      suffering and TMD pain is the most common symptom that compels patients to seek therapy. One
      study found average ratings of pain intensity due to TMD of 4.3 on a 10-point scale, similar
      to the averages reported for chest pain and back pain.  Studies consistently find that TMD
      has a pronounced impact on quality of life. Thus, a new successful approach to TMD therapy
      would have a significant clinical and economic impact.

      Caloric vestibular stimulation (CVS) is a routine diagnostic test for the assessment of
      vestibular function and CNS pathology. It is usually conducted by instilling cold or warm
      water into the external ear canal and has been shown to activate anterior cingulate,
      temporoparietal and insular cortices. In addition to its use as a diagnostic test, CVS has
      also been shown to reduce pain in several chronic conditions including migraine, phantom
      limb pain, spinal cord injury, thalamic pain, and complex regional pain syndrome.

      Central sensitization is a common feature of the pain conditions shown to be alleviated by
      CVS. It is a dysfunctional state of the central nervous system in which pain is no longer
      coupled to a noxious peripheral stimulus. In the presence of central sensitization the
      response to a noxious stimulus is exaggerated and prolonged (hyperalgesia) and may involve
      areas outside the site of injury (secondary hyperalgesia).  Pain can also arise
      spontaneously and can be elicited by innocuous stimuli (allodynia). While the neural
      mechanisms underlying the development of TMD are poorly understood, there is accumulating
      evidence that central sensitization plays a critical role in TMD pathogenesis. It has been
      proposed that there is a cyclical process in which TMD pain results in central sensitization
      that in turn predisposes patients to more pain. Thus any treatment that reverses central
      sensitization should in turn result in a decrease in pain.

      Caloric vestibular stimulation (CVS) is a safe and effective procedure used for the
      diagnosis of brainstem injury and for balance assessment.  As noted already, there have been
      intriguing observations in the literature suggesting that caloric vestibular stimulation can
      lead to the abatement of pain.  When a caloric stimulation (warm or cool relative to body
      temperature) is applied to the ear canal, conduction (primarily via dense bone) to the inner
      ear, and in particular the prominence of the lateral semicircular canal (SCC), sets up
      convection currents in the endolymph. The resultant deformation of the cupula (membrane
      spanning the ampula of the SCC) leads to a phasic change in the tonic firing rate of hair
      cells at the base of the cupula, thereby altering the firing rate of the afferents of the
      vestibular nerve (thus a device delivering CVS may be viewed as a class of neurostimulator).
      The afferents map to nuclei in the brainstem (as well as some phylogenetically ancient,
      direct connections, e.g. to the thalamus and hippocampus) and then to the fastigial nuclei
      in the cerebellum. It is hypothesized that the method of action of CVS on pain relates to
      alteration of the phasic firing rate in the vestibular nerve afferents, which in turn alters
      the activation of the receiving areas (brainstem and cerebellum).

      The primary impediment to therapeutic applications of CVS has been the lack of a clinical
      device that provides controlled, prolonged, and repeatable caloric stimulation.  The use of
      &quot;ice water&quot; irrigation using syringes or even the water/air irrigators used in balance
      studies are not practical for treatment regimens that extend up to 10 minutes.  Further, the
      applicants believe that a controlled, time-varying thermal waveform is essential to avoid
      the effects of adaptation of the cupula, which then attenuates control of the phasic firing
      rate of the hair cells.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>pain intensity as reported on the VAS</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in composite pain index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, weeks 1,2,3,4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in signs and symptoms of TMD based on outcomes of RDC exam</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, weeks 1,2,3,4</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Temporomandibular Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Caloric Vestibular Neurostimulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Scion Neurostim, LLC, Caloric Vestibular Neurostimulation Device</intervention_name>
    <description>3 treatments over 1week, caloric vestibular neurostimulation for 7.5 minutes in the right ear</description>
    <arm_group_label>Caloric Vestibular Neurostimulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged 18-65 years

          -  English speaking

          -  Females with chronic TMD

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of any of the following: Terminal, progressive and /or unstable medical
             illness; Previous head or neck surgery for neoplasm; current chemotherapy or
             radiation therapy; facial trauma or orofacial surgery within the last 6 weeks;
             seizures, history of drug or alcohol abuse; Otologic  disorders including chronic
             vertigo, chronic tinnitus, otitis external, otitis media, mastoiditis and tympanic
             membrane perforation; Stroke, transient ischemia attacks or Arnold- Chiari
             malformation; significant cardiac or respiratory disease; epilepsy or neurological
             disorders such as dementia, brain injury, and brain tumor

          -  Subjects who score ≥31 on the Becks depression inventory (performed at first
             appointment)

          -  History of or current destructive nerve therapies, defibrillator, pacemakers, deep
             brain stimulator, or Implantable nerve stimulators

          -  Utilization of other alternative or complementary therapies during the study period

          -  Participation in a clinical trial involving the use of a clinical devise in the last
             30 days

          -  Women who are currently pregnant or nursing.

          -  Patients who are left handed.

          -  Current orthodontic treatment.

          -  Use of an opiate in the 48 hour period preceding the baseline study visit

          -  The use of anti-histamines 6 hours before, during or immediately after the treatment
             period

          -  The use of anti-nausea or anti-vertigo drugs 6 hours before or during the treatment
             period
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Asma Khan, BDS, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill School of Dentistry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 3, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 6, 2011</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Asma Khan, BDS, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor UNC School of Dentistry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Single blind</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomized</keyword>
  <keyword>Controlled clinical trial</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Temporomandibular Joint Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Temporomandibular Joint Dysfunction Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
