<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 19, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01073436</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UMCC 2008.083</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HUM00021950</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01073436</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Discontinuation of Imatinib Mesylate in Patients With Chronic-Phase Chronic Myeloid Leukemia Previously Treated With Interferon-Alpha</brief_title>
  <official_title>Discontinuation of Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor Therapy in Patients With Chronic-Phase Chronic Myeloid Leukemia, Previously Treated With Interferon-Alpha</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To investigate whether patients with chronic-phase chronic myeloid leukemia (CP-CML)
      previously treated with interferon-alpha (IFN) and presently on a tyrosine kinase inhibitor
      (TKI) (imatinib mesylate, dasatinib, or nilotinib) with achievement of a complete
      cytogenetic and at least a major molecular remission, are able to discontinue therapy and
      maintain a durable remission. Relapse-free survival (RFS) rate at 1 year after
      discontinuation of TKI will be the measurement of this objective.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case-Only, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Relapse-free survival (RFS) rate at 1 year after discontinuation of TKI will be the measurement of this objective.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction of the malignant stem cell population</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To determine whether prior treatment with interferon-alpha followed by TKI therapy effectively depletes/reduces the malignant stem cell population in CP-CML.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Discontinuation</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects who agree to discontinue their tyrosine kinase inhibitor(TKI)therapy, namely,imatinib mesylate, dasatinib, or nilotinib,and then followed to see if they can maintain a durable remission.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Discontinuation of therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with chronic-phase chronic myeloid leukemia (CP-CML) previously treated with interferon-alpha (IFN) and presently on a tyrosine kinase inhibitor (TKI) (imatinib mesylate, dasatinib, or nilotinib) with achievement of a complete cytogenetic and at least a major molecular remission.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Discontinuation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Diagnosed with Philadelphia chromosome positive (Ph+) chronic myeloid leukemia in chronic
        phase.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients must have a diagnosis of Philadelphia chromosome positive (Ph+) chronic
             myeloid leukemia in chronic phase.

          2. Patients must have received prior therapy with interferon-alpha for their CML, for a
             period of at least 2 years, and achieved at least a partial cytogenetic response on
             this therapy, defined as 1% - 34% Ph+ cells in metaphase, present in the bone marrow.

          3. Patients must be actively receiving treatment for their CML with a TKI (imatinib
             mesylate, dasatinib, nilotinib). If patients are receiving dasatinib or nilotinib,
             this can only be for reasons other than imatinib-resistant CML.

          4. Patients must have an ongoing complete hematologic response (CHR) on a TKI, defined
             as follows:

               -  WBC ≤ 10 x 109/L.

               -  Platelet count &lt; 450,000 x 109/L.

               -  No blasts or promyelocytes in peripheral blood.

               -  No evidence of disease-related symptoms and extramedullary disease, including
                  the liver and spleen.

          5. Patients must have a complete cytogenetic response (CCyR) on a TKI for a minimum of
             one year leading up to enrollment. Complete cytogenetic response is defined as 0% Ph+
             cells in metaphase, in the bone marrow and/or a negative peripheral blood FISH
             analysis for the BCR/ABL gene fusion, and an ongoing CCyR must be confirmed by bone
             marrow aspirate cytogenetics and/or peripheral blood FISH for BCR/ABL within 4 weeks
             of discontinuing therapy.

          6. Patients must have at least a major molecular remission on a TKI for a minimum of 1
             year, present on 2 consecutive analyses, performed at least 3 months apart, in the 6
             to 12 months leading up to enrollment. Major molecular remission is defined as ≥ 3
             log reduction from a standard baseline value (equivalent to a BCR-ABL/ABL of ≤ 0.1%)
             in BCR/ABL transcript by quantitative RT-PCR performed on peripheral blood or bone
             marrow aspirate.  Complete molecular remission is defined as a negative quantitative
             RT-PCR (QPCR) analysis for BCR/ABL, present on 2 consecutive analyses, performed at
             least 3 months apart, in the 6 to 12 months leading up to enrollment.

          7. Patients must be eighteen years of age or older

          8. Patients must have an ECOG performance status of 0-2 (Appendix 13.1)

          9. All patients must be informed of the investigational nature of this study and
             standard alternative therapy. All patients must sign and give written informed
             consent in accordance with institutional and federal guidelines.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who have had prior progression of their CML to accelerated phase or blast
             crisis.

          2. Patients who have previously undergone hematopoietic stem cell transplantation.

          3. Patients receiving dasatinib or nilotinib due to a prior history of
             imatinib-resistant CML.

          4. Patients with a history of non-compliance to medical regimens or who are considered
             potentially unreliable.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dale Bixby, M.D./PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 9, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 19, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>diagnosis of Ph+) CML in chronic phase.</keyword>
  <keyword>prior therapy with interferon-alpha for at least 2 years, and achieved at least a partial cytogenetic response</keyword>
  <keyword>receiving a TKI (imatinib mesylate, dasatinib, nilotinib)</keyword>
  <keyword>WBC ≤ 10 x 109/L.</keyword>
  <keyword>Platelet count &lt; 450,000 x 109/L.</keyword>
  <keyword>No blasts or promyelocytes in peripheral blood.</keyword>
  <keyword>No evidence of disease-related symptoms and extramedullary disease</keyword>
  <keyword>complete cytogenetic response (CCyR) on a TKI for a minimum of 1 yr</keyword>
  <keyword>major molecular remission on a TKI for a minimum of 1 yr</keyword>
  <keyword>18 years of age or older</keyword>
  <keyword>ECOG performance status of 0-2 (Appendix 13.1)</keyword>
  <keyword>Informed Consent</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelogenous, Chronic, BCR-ABL Positive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Chronic-Phase</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Interferon-alpha</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Interferon Alfa-2a</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Interferons</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Imatinib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dasatinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
