<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 19, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00181896</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2004-P-001727</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00181896</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bupropion SR for Major Depression and Depression NOS in Children and Adolescents With Bipolar Disorder</brief_title>
  <official_title>Open-Label Study of Bupropion SR for Major Depression and Depression NOS in Children and Adolescents With Bipolar and Bipolar Spectrum Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an 8-week open label study of bupropion SR in the treatment of youth with bipolar
      depression with adequate mood stabilization.  All youth will be closely monitored for
      treatment emergent manic activation and drug-drug interactions with ongoing antimanic
      agents.

      The main objective of this study is to assess the safety and effectiveness of bupropion SR
      in the treatment of bipolar depression in children and adolescents.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      While anti-manic agents can effectively control manic symptoms, bipolar patients frequently
      continue to struggle with residual depressive symptomatology that can be associated with
      severe morbidity and suicidality.  Because antidepressants can activate manic symptoms in
      bipolar patients with depression, the treatment of bipolar depression poses unique and
      challenging therapeutic dilemmas Thus, the identification of appropriate safe and effective
      treatment strategies for the management of depression in bipolar youth is particularly
      taxing considering that pediatric mania is predominantly mixed with a strong depressive
      component. A recent study in our program of bupropion SR in 30 adults with ADHD and Bipolar
      disorder, treatment with bupropion SR was extremely well tolerated and was not associated
      with activation of manic symptoms. Because bupropion has not been evaluated in the treatment
      of bipolar depression in youth, there is a pressing need to evaluate its effectiveness and
      safety in the context of a treatment protocol aimed at carefully evaluating this issue.

      This is an 8-week open label study of bupropion SR in the treatment of youth with bipolar
      depression with adequate mood stabilization.  All youth will be closely monitored for
      treatment emergent manic activation and drug-drug interactions with ongoing antimanic
      agents.

      The main objective of this study is to assess the safety and effectiveness of bupropion SR
      in the treatment of bipolar depression in children and adolescents.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Study was terminated due to lack of recruitment
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>January 2005</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>reduction in depression symptoms assessed by</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Children's Depression Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hamilton Depression Rating scale (HAM-D)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Bipolar Disorder</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>bupropion SR</intervention_name>
    <description>Open-label prescription of Bupropion SR for 8 weeks.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Males and females age 6 to 17 with a diagnosis of current depression with bipolar
             disorder based on clinical assessment and confirmed by structured diagnostic
             interview plus an initial Hamilton rating scale score &gt;17 and a Young Mania Rating
             Score of &lt; 15.

          -  Children will only be allowed to participate in the trial if they have had mood
             stabilization on a steady dose of medication for at least 2 months.  By mood
             stabilization we mean as determined by principle investigator, evaluator clinician,
             and as confirmed by KSADS.

          -  Subject and parent must have a level of understanding sufficient to communicate
             intelligently with the investigator and study coordinator, and to cooperate with all
             tests and examinations required by the protocol.

          -  Subjects and their legal representative must be considered reliable.

          -  Each subject and his/her authorized legal representative must understand the nature
             of the study.  The subject's authorized legal representative must sign an informed
             consent document and the subject must sign an informed assent document.

          -  Subject must be able to participate in mandatory blood draws.

          -  Subject must be able to swallow pills.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects with chronic medical illness, DSM-IV substance dependence within the past month,
        pregnant or nursing female subjects will be excluded from this study.

          -  Investigator and his/her immediate family; defined as the investigator's spouse,
             parent, child, grandparent, or grandchild.

          -  Serious, unstable illness including hepatic, renal, gastroenterological, respiratory,
             cardiovascular, endocrine, neurologic, immunologic, or hematologic disease.

          -  History of severe allergies or multiple adverse drug reactions.

          -  Non-febrile seizures without a clear and resolved etiology.

          -  Leukopenia or history of leukopenia without a clear and resolved etiology.

          -  Judged clinically to be at serious suicidal risk.

          -  Acute Psychosis

          -  Any other concomitant medication with primarily central nervous system activity other
             than specified in Concomitant Medication portion of the protocol.

          -  History of intolerance or non-response to bupropion.

          -  Treatment with nonreversible monoamine oxidase inhibitor within 2 weeks prior to
             initiation of study.

          -  Current diagnosis of schizophrenia.

          -  History of head trauma

          -  CNS tumor

          -  Diabetic treated with oral hypoglycemics or insulin

          -  Current or prior diagnosis of bulimia or anorexia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joseph Biederman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cambridge</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02138</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 14, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 13, 2005</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Joseph Biederman, MD</name_title>
    <organization>Massachusetts General Hospital</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>depression</keyword>
  <keyword>bipolar disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>children</keyword>
  <keyword>bupropion SR</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Bipolar Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Bupropion</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
