<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 22, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00308100</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BFP502</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00308100</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hydroxyethyl Starch (130/0.4) for Intravascular Volume Therapy in Liver Transplantation</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multicenter, Randomized, Open-Label, Parallel-Group, Albumin-Controlled Phase IV Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Hydroxyethyl Starch (130/0.4) for Intravascular Volume Therapy in Patients Undergoing Liver Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fresenius Kabi</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fresenius Kabi</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>China: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      There are no standardized plasma volume replacement protocols during liver transplantation
      surgery. The current study is designed to compare efficacy, safety, and costs of
      perioperative volume replacement with Voluven (Hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4) and albumin in
      patients undergoing liver transplantation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      End-stage liver disease is one of the major diseases leading to death. With advancement of
      transplantation surgery and perioperative anesthesia management, liver transplantation has
      become an effective method to recover patients' liver function, thus saving their lives and
      improving their quality of life. Serious disorders of fluid balance, such as blood
      coagulation dysfunction, electrolyte disequilibrium, hypoalbuminaemia, low hematocrit, low
      hemoglobin and acid-base imbalance etc. exist in end stage cirrhosis patients with liver
      transplantation. Such abnormalities in the internal milieu could cause or worsen
      cardiovascular and pulmonary dysfunction, thus making perioperative management more
      difficult.

      Albumin and blood plasma are conventionally used as plasma volume expanders in clinical
      practice. At the same time, the level of albumin concentration is also used as an important
      criterion of prognosis. When the level of albumin concentration in serum is below 35 g/L,
      postoperative mortality rates and complications will increase significantly. In fact, it has
      been the focus of debate for many years whether albumin should be used for volume
      replacement in critically ill patients. Boldt and his colleagues demonstrated that albumin
      has little positive influence on the prognosis of critically ill patients. However, Shwe
      deemed albumin beneficial to critically ill patients. Simon suggested that albumin is given
      mainly for treating hypovolemia instead of increasing the level of albumin concentration in
      serum. However, at the same time, he admitted there is no advantages of albumin in
      comparison to other colloid solutions and, furthermore, it is more expensive.

      Voluven (130/0.4) is a medium molecular weight hydroxyethyl starch (HES) produced by Beijing
      Fresenius Kabi Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd. It is a novel HES preparation with optimized
      molecular weight and molecule distribution, has a lower degree of substitution (DS) (0.4),
      and a narrower molecular distribution profile (C2/C6) than other available HES
      specifications which make it more suitable for volume replacement therapy. Some studies have
      revealed that Voluven (130/0.4) has a comparable efficacy with HAES-steril (average
      molecular weight 200.000 dalton, degree of substitution 0.5). Because of its improved
      pharmacological profile, Voluven (130/0.4) is used to avoid capillary vessel leakage and
      improve oxygenation of tissues. In addition, Voluven (130/0.4) does not accumulate in plasma
      or tissues even after multiple dosing (maximal dose 50 ml/kg), and has an improved HES
      safety profile in terms of coagulation and kidney function.

      The current study is designed to assess the efficacy, safety, and pharmaceutical economics
      characteristic of perioperative volume replacement with Voluven (130/0.4) in patients
      undergoing liver transplantation compared with patients who received volume therapy with
      albumin. The objective of this study is to supply appropriate regimens for patients
      undergoing liver transplantation, considering clinical efficacy, safety, and costs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Study is prematurely ended due to poor patient recruitment rate.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>October 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemodynamics</measure>
    <time_frame>From pre-operative period till discharged from hospital</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child-Turcotte-Pugh (CTP) score</measure>
    <time_frame>From pre-operative period till discharged from hospital</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Model for End-Stage Liver Disease (MELD) score</measure>
    <time_frame>From pre-operative period till discharged from hospital</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">53</enrollment>
  <condition>Intraoperative Complications</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hydroxyethylstarch 130/0.4</intervention_name>
    <description>HES 130/0.4, administered intra- and perioperatively, max. daily dose: 33ml/kg BW; if needed, additionally albumin is administered (ratio crystalloid to colloid= 1:1)</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>HES 130/0.4</other_name>
    <other_name>Hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>5% Albumin</intervention_name>
    <description>5% albumin, administered intra- and perioperatively</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged 18-65 years, male or female

          -  Elective liver transplantation

          -  United Network for Organ Sharing (UNOS) Level 2A/B or 3

          -  Serum albumin ≥ 30 g/L

          -  Comprehend all the procedures of this study

          -  Willing and able to give informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Uncontrolled exo-hepatic malignant carcinomas

          -  Uncontrollable infections (including HIV infection)

          -  Need support of artificial liver or kidney, ventilator-dependant, coma or    unstable
             hemodynamically

          -  Patients with a history of hypersensitivity to hydroxyethyl starch or albumin

          -  Urinary output less than 500 ml within 24 hours after operation

          -  Patients with intracranial bleeding

          -  Patients with other colloids for treating hypovolemia

          -  Patients with pulmonary edema

          -  Pregnant women or females of childbearing potential and lactating mothers

          -  Patients who are participating in other drug studies or who receive other
             investigational drugs within 30 days prior to the present study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Xisheng Leng, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>People's University of Peking University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>People's Hospital of Peking University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <zip>100044</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2009</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 14, 2009</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 28, 2006</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Professor Leng Xisheng</name_title>
    <organization>Beijing Renmin Hospital</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Liver Transplantation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Intraoperative Complications</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hetastarch</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
