<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 22, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01661400</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201209088</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01661400</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Anti-Angiogenic Therapy Post Transplant (ASCR) for Relapsed and Refractory Pediatric Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <acronym>ASCR</acronym>
  <official_title>Anti-Angiogenic Therapy After Autologous Stem Cell Rescue (ASCR) for Relapsed and Refractory Pediatric Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research study is to determine whether taking either of two low dose
      drugs that would prevent new blood vessels from growing after stem cell transplant is
      feasible, and what the side effects of taking each of these drugs after autologous
      transplant might be.  The reason the investigators are looking at these drugs is because one
      of the things that allows tumors to grow quickly is their ability to stimulate the growth of
      new blood vessels.  By suppressing the growth of new blood vessels after stem cell
      transplant, the investigators hope to prevent the tumors from coming back or continuing to
      grow.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 0</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>Minimum of 2 years after inititation of study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured by absence of grade 4 or 5 non-hematological or grade 5 hematological toxicity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>Minimum of 2 years after inititation of study treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured by absence of grade 4 or 5 non-hematological or grade 5 hematological toxicity from baseline to Day +30</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiographic marker of neovascularization</measure>
    <time_frame>86 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measurement of anti-angiogenic activity in the treatment of solid tumors from baseline to Day +86.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Best overall response</measure>
    <time_frame>86 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Assessed by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) guideline version 1.1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Glioma</condition>
  <condition>Neuroectodermal Tumors, Primitive</condition>
  <condition>Wilms Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Rhabdomyosarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Sarcoma, Ewing</condition>
  <condition>Osteosarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Retinoblastoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Metronomic Cyclophosphamide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cyclophosphamide will be given PO once daily at 2.5 mg/kg/day for children &lt; 40kg or 100 mg daily for children &gt; 40kg beginning Day + 30 (30 days post transplant) and continue until at least Day +86</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Thalidomide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Thalidomide will be initiated at 3mg/kg PO daily beginning Day + 30 (30 days post transplant) and continue until Day +86</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metronomic Cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Metronomic Cyclophosphamide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cytoxan®</other_name>
    <other_name>CPM</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Thalidomide</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Thalidomide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Thalomid®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient must have an original diagnosis, benefited by autologous transplantation,
             confirmed by biopsy* of high-grade glial tumor, low-grade glial tumor, ependymoma,
             medulloblastoma, primitive neuro-ectodermal tumor (PNET), Wilms' tumor,
             rhabdomyosarcoma, Ewing's sarcoma, retinoblastoma, or miscellaneous poor-prognosis
             solid tumors.  Lymphomas and other lymphoid malignancies will not be studied in this
             protocol.

             * Brain stem glioma patients who have progressed after radiation therapy do not
             require histologic confirmation. Brain stem gliomas are defined as intrinsic tumors
             of the pons causing diffuse enlargement.  These patients are diagnosed on clinical
             and radiographic appearance of the lesion and the biopsy requirement will be waived
             for this group.

          -  Patient must be ≥ 1 years of age and ≤ 21 years of age at the time of study entry.

          -  Patient must have a Karnofsky performance status or Lansky* play status ≥ 50

             * For purpose of determining performance scores, wheelchair-bound patients will be
             considered ambulatory.

          -  Patient must have an adequate supply of stem cells for transplant harvested prior to
             study enrollment, with adequate supply defined as 3 x 106 CD34+ cells/kg for
             peripheral blood stem cells (PBSC).  Cell mobilization method will be left up to the
             treating physician's discretion and may include mobilization growth factor alone or
             mobilization after chemotherapy.  If patient is unable to mobilize the proper amount
             of peripheral stem cells, bone marrow may be harvested as the source of hematopoietic
             stem cells.  In this instance, 3 x 108 mononuclear cells/kg will be considered
             adequate.  If necessary, a combination of peripheral stem cells and bone marrow can
             be used.

          -  Prior radiation therapy and/or chemotherapy, including cyclophosphamide, are
             permitted.

          -  Prior anti-angiogenic therapy, including thalidomide and oral cyclophosphamide, is
             permitted.

          -  If on corticosteroids for mass effect and/or edema related to the tumor, patient must
             be on a stable dose for at least 2 weeks prior to study entry.

          -  Patient must have a life expectancy &gt; 2 months.

          -  Patient must have an adequate bone marrow reserve as defined by:

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dl and

               -  Platelet count ≥ 30,000/ mm3 (transfusion independent) and

               -  Peripheral absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 750/mm3

          -  Patient must have adequate cardiac function tested within 4 weeks of study enrollment
             as defined by:

               -  Shortening fraction of ≥ 27% by echocardiogram or

               -  Ejection fraction of ≥ 50% by radionuclide angiogram

          -  Patient must have adequate pulmonary function tested within 4 weeks of study
             enrollment as defined by:

               -  Pulse oximetry &gt; 94% on room air or O2 by nasal cannula and

               -  No evidence of dyspnea at rest.

          -  Patient must have adequate hepatic function as defined by:

               -  Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5x upper limit of normal (ULN) for age and

               -  SGOT (AST) or SGPT (ALT) ≤ 2.5 x ULN (SGOT ≤ 4x ULN if on Zantac)

          -  Patient must have adequate renal function as defined by:

               -  Serum creatinine &lt; 1.5 mg/dl

               -  Glomerular filtration rate (GFR), calculated via I-125 iothalamate clearance,
                  24-hour creatinine clearance, or Schwartz formula*, ≥ 70 mL/min and ≥ 50
                  mL/min/1.73 m2 done within 4 weeks of study entry

               -  The Schwartz formula is an estimated glomerular filtration rate in children
                  based upon serum creatinine and height.  Height (Ht) should be measured in cm
                  and serum creatinine (Cr) in mg/dL.  Proportionality constant (k) is 0.55 for
                  children and adolescent girls and 0.7 for adolescent boys aged 13-21.  This
                  constant is based upon a series of evaluations performed by Schwartz.   Formula:
                   GFR= (k x Ht)/Cr

          -  If female of childbearing potential (defined as menstruating or amenorrheic from
             previous medical treatments), the following guidelines must be adhered to:

               -  If enrolled in Arm III of this study, patient must be registered at the Celgene
                  S.T.E.P.S. ® Program.

               -  If enrolled in Arm III of this study, patient must be willing to practice birth
                  control as outlined in the S.T.E.P.S. Program from the beginning of the study
                  until at least 4 weeks following discontinuation of thalidomide therapy.  Two
                  reliable forms of contraception must be used simultaneously unless continuous
                  abstinence from heterosexual sexual contact is chosen.  Contraceptive methods
                  must include at least one highly effective method (e.g. oral contraceptive
                  pills, injections, hormonal patches, IUD, or implants), AND one additional
                  effective barrier method (e.g. latex condom, diaphragm, cervical cap).  If
                  hormonal or IUD contraception is medically contraindicated, another highly
                  effective method or two barrier methods must be used at the same time.

          -  Pregnancy surveillance:

               -  Patient must have a negative in office pregnancy test sensitive to within 50
                  mIU/mL (serum or urine) within 24 hours of beginning thalidomide even if
                  continuous abstinence is the preferred method of birth control.

               -  A pregnancy test must be performed weekly during the first 4 weeks of therapy
                  and repeated monthly for patients with regular menses or every 2 weeks for
                  patients with irregular menses

               -  Negative pregnancy tests are valid for only 7 days.

               -  If irregular bleeding or skipped menses, pregnancy test should be performed and
                  pregnancy counseling given.

               -  If pregnancy occurs during treatment, thalidomide must be immediately
                  discontinued.  Any suspected lethal exposure must be reported immediately to
                  Celgene Customer Care Center at 1-888-423-5346, and the patient referred to an
                  OB/GYN experienced in reproductive toxicity for further evaluation and
                  counseling.

          -  Patient (or legally authorized representative) must be able to understand and willing
             to sign a written informed consent document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient must not have any active, uncontrolled cardiac, hepatic, renal, or
             psychiatric disease defined as ≥ grade 3 based on NCI Common Terminology Criteria for
             Adverse Events v4.0 (CTCAE).

          -  Patient must not be receiving any other investigational agents.

          -  Patient must not have any active infection or concurrent illness obscuring toxicity
             or dangerously altering drug metabolism.

          -  Patient must not have any thromboembolic event (deep vein thrombosis or pulmonary
             embolism) less than 3 weeks prior to enrollment.

          -  Patient must not have a history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of
             similar chemical or biologic composition to any of the agents used in the study.

          -  Patient must not be pregnant or breastfeeding.

        Inclusion of Women and Minorities

        -Both men and women and members of all races and ethnic groups are eligible for this
        trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lisa Madden, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lisa Madden, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>314-454-6018</phone>
    <email>madden_l@kids.wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63122</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lisa Madden, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>314-454-6018</phone>
      <email>madden_l@kids.wustl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert Hayashi, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Shalini Shenoy, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeffrey Bednarski, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Monica Hente, ARNP</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Geetika Khanna, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joshua Shimony, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.siteman.wustl.edu</url>
    <description>Alvin J. Siteman Cancer Center at Barnes-Jewish Hospital and Washington University School of Medicine</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 16, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 30, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Glioma includes ependymoma and medulloblastoma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wilms Tumor</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteosarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinoblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rhabdomyosarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neuroectodermal Tumors</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neuroectodermal Tumors, Primitive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma, Ewing's</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Angiogenesis Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
