<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 19, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02032589</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>698-11 GE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02032589</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Testing the Efficacy of Self-Generation Treatment Protocol</brief_title>
  <official_title>Exploring the Effects of a Memory Intervention on Memory and Everyday Life Activities With Persons With MS</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kessler Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Multiple Sclerosis Society</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kessler Foundation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Past research has shown that items self-generated by an individual, such as words or
      concepts, are remembered better than items that are simply read or heard. The current study
      seeks to demonstrate the effectiveness of using the principles of the generation effect in a
      treatment intervention to improve memory and functional performance in individuals with
      Multiple Sclerosis who have learning and memory difficulties.The main purpose of the study
      is to conduct an experimental investigation on the effects of a self-generation strategy
      treatment, embedded within practice of various activities ranging from laboratory tasks
      (e.g. words and concepts) to functional tasks (e.g. activities of daily living). The
      treatment to be tested is geared toward helping patients selfdiscover their own strengths
      and abilities while using self-generation to be able to utilize it independently in everyday
      life situations.

      Design: The proposed pilot study is a randomized clinical trial. Participants: Participants
      will include forty (40) persons with MS, between the ages of 18 and 65, who demonstrate
      memory impairments. Half of the participants will receive the self-generation training while
      learning different types of tasks (experimental group) and half of the participants (control
      group) will be asked to learn the same information but will receive a conventional practice
      (e.g. repetitions).

      Expected results: We expect that participants undergoing the self-generation-training
      intervention will show better memory performance, functional performance, quality of life,
      and satisfaction with treatment and life compared to participants in the control condition.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      If self- generation can be successfully adapted and applied to a treatment program for
      individuals with MS, it has the potential to improve their rehabilitation and treatment by
      facilitating new learning and memory. In addition, if treatment and rehabilitation are
      successful and productive, it is expected that the application of self-generation strategy
      to improve learning/ relearning will help to improve the ability of individuals with MS to
      maintain their current lifestyles at home, work, and within the community. We expect that
      persons with MS who complete the proposed treatment will acquire the trained strategy,
      recognize the everyday situations in which the trained strategy could be applied and then
      map and adapt the trained strategy to real-world situations.

      Fourty participants with clinically definite MS and objectively documented impairment in
      verbal new learning will be included in the study. Participants will be randomly assigned to
      either the treatment group (n=20) or the control group (n=20).  Participants will be
      enrolled only following an informed consent procedure, with the expectation of being able to
      participate for the full duration of the study (6 treatment sessions and two assessment
      sessions).  All participants enrolled in the study will undergo pre and post treatment
      assessment to assess their levels of cognitive, emotional, and functional performance.
      Treatment for both experimental and control groups will consist of 6 individualized
      treatment sessions, 2 x per week for 3 weeks.   Each session will last for approximately 45
      minutes, and will include various memory tasks that will range from learning list of words
      to learning tasks related to everyday life.  Participants in the control group will only be
      asked to perform the same memory tasks as the treatment group. The treatment for the
      experimental group will couple self-generated learning with awareness-training techniques,
      which are geared toward helping patients self-discover their performance strengths and
      limitations through integration of direct and personal experiences. Personal experience will
      be gained by practicing various memory tasks using self-generation strategy. This proposed
      self-generation program is expected to increase memory, task specific awareness and
      functional performance; ultimately improving quality of life and self-regulation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropsychological Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline assessment, and Week 3</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of Global Functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 3</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Self-generation treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>self-generation strategy treatment, embedded within practice of various activities</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>memory training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment consists on traditional memory training</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Self-generation treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>self-generation treatment is a cognitive rehabilitation strategy aimed to improve  memory. The self-generation strategy treatment, embedded within practice of various activities will consists of six individualized intervention sessions administered over 2-3 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Self-generation treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of Multiple sclerosis

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of other neurological conditions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yael Goverover, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kessler Foundation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John DeLuca, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kessler Foundation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yael Goverover, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>212-998-5854</phone>
    <email>yg243@nyu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nancy B Moore, MA</last_name>
    <phone>973-324-8450</phone>
    <email>nbmoore@kesslerfoundation.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kessler Foundation</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Orange</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07052</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nancy B Moore, MA</last_name>
      <phone>973-324-8450</phone>
      <email>nbmoore@kesslerfoundation.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John DeLuca, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 9, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 19, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Kessler Foundation</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Yael Goverover</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Visiting Scientist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
