<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 19, 2014</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00209170</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01 MH069254-03</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01 MH069254-03</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00209170</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Depression- Diabetes Mechanisms: Urban African Americans</brief_title>
  <official_title>Depression- Diabetes Mechanisms: Urban African Americans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Forest Laboratories</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      African-Americans suffer from increased prevalence of both type 2 diabetes and diabetes
      complications, reflecting a combination of psychobehavioral factors as well as metabolic
      dysfunction.  In this process, depression may contribute to both the genesis of type 2
      diabetes (through impact on neurohormonal activation, inflammatory mediators, and insulin
      resistance), and difficulties in management (through decreased adherence to diet plans,
      medication, and scheduled appointments). Our preliminary data from the Grady Diabetes Clinic
      indicates that depression may be common in African-Americans with diabetes, that depression
      is a factor in non-adherence, and that non-adherence leads to poor glycemic control - a
      direct cause of diabetes complications.  What is not known is: how treatment of depression
      could lead to both neurohormonal and psychobiological improvement, with improved patient
      adherence and glycemic control.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To determine the psychobehavioral and neurohormonal mechanisms of effective treatment, we
      will conduct a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial in patients with major
      depression, who will receive either:  (i) computer-based cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT)
      program entitled &quot;Beating the Blues&quot; + placebo, or (ii) computer-based cognitive behavioral
      therapy (CBT) program entitled &quot;Beating the Blues&quot; + the SSRI antidepressant escitalopram.
      We will assess (a) glycemic control (levels of HbA1c), in relation to (b) adherence (keeping
      scheduled return appointments, diet, exercise, and glucose monitoring), (c) depressive
      symptoms (neurocognitive and neurobehavioral symptoms determined by self- and observer-rated
      scales), and (d) the four pathways of neurometabolic function.

      Study visits will occur once a month for 6 months.  Should patients report severe
      environmental stressors (such as marital conflict, loss of family member or job, being
      exposed to trauma), patients will be offered an intensification of their contact with study
      personnel, e.g. weekly contact by phone or &quot;in-person&quot; visits to see study personnel at the
      Grady Diabetes Clinic.

      After completion of 6 months, patients may enter an open-label treatment with escitalopram
      or be tapered off their study medication.  If patients develop worsening depressed mood, at
      any time during the study they will be offered treatment with open-label escitalopram or an
      alternative antidepressant for the remainder of the 52 weeks of the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Double-Blind, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Glycemic control: Assessed as levels of HbA1c:</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neurometabolic Variables:  The impact of treatment on changes in HPA axis activation, sympathomedullary and other counter-regulatory hormones, immunoinflammatory factors, and insulin resistance.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence:  The maintenance of scheduled appointments will be measured both by patients who keep their one-year appointments or not, and among those who return at one year, the percentage of interim appointments kept.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Variability in followup:  Since it is likely that some patients will not return for all scheduled follow-up appointments, we will compare characteristics of patients who dropped out vs. those who did not in the escitalopram and placebo groups.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>We will also compare changes in HbA1c and adherence in the two treatment arms (n=250 each) with the two groups from Aim #1 - depressed patients given &quot;usual care&quot; (n=500) and nondepressed patients (n=3000).</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Behavior Therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lexapro</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects must be English-speaking

          -  African American

          -  Have type 2 diabetes per American Diabetes Association criteria

          -  Patient's receiving care at Grady Hospital

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Severely depressed (Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (HAM-D) ≥ 34

          -  Non - English speaking

          -  Women who are pregnant, women who will be breastfeeding during the study, and women
             of childbearing potential who are not practicing a reliable method of birth control.

          -  currently meet DSM-IV criteria for:

          -  Bipolar Disorder

          -  Schizophrenia or any Psychotic Disorder

          -  Obsessive Compulsive Disorder

          -  Mental Retardation or any Pervasive Developmental Disorder or Cognitive Disorder.

          -  Personality Disorder of sufficient severity to interfere with their participation in
             the study

          -  Psychotic features or with history of Psychotic Disorder, as defined by DSM-IV

          -  Suicide risk, or have made serious suicide attempt in the past year

          -  Substance Abuse or Dependence (other than nicotine) during the six months preceding
             the first dose of double blind study medication

          -  Any malignancy (other than excised basal cell carcinoma), or any clinically
             significant hematological, endocrine, cardiovascular (including any rhythm disorder),
             renal, hepatic, gastrointestinal, or neurological disease.   History of syndrome of
             inappropriate anti-diuretic hormone secretion.

          -  Diabetes due to: glucagonoma, pheochromocytoma or other endocrine neoplasm, drug
             induced diabetes, gestational diabetes, or those with established genetic defects of
             beta cell function.

          -  Medical conditions that will interfere with the HbA1c assay or if hospitalization is
             likely within two months (sickle cell anemia, hypersplenism)

          -  A history of diabetic ketoacidosis episode during the 6 months preceding the first
             dose of double-blind study medication.

          -  Uncontrolled diabetes as judged by the investigator defined as blood glucose greater
             than 400 on last two visits or patients whom suffered from diabetic ketoacidosis in
             the last month or have had 2 episodes in the last year.

          -  Autonomic or peripheral neuropathy that requires treatment

          -  At the first follow-up visit - Patients with systolic blood pressure greater than 180
             mm Hg or less than 90 mm Hg or diastolic blood pressure greater than 105 mm Hg or
             less than 50 mm Hg

          -  Treatment with a depot neuroleptic during the last 6 months

          -  Patients who have been treated with any neuroleptic, antidepressant, or anxiolytic
             medication OR ANY OF THE MEDS BELOW during in the last 2 weeks (8 weeks for
             fluoxetine)

             1-(Aminomethyl)cyclohexaneacetic acid 5-Hydroxytryptamine Alprazolam
             Amitriptyline-doses greater than 50 mg/day Amoxapine-doses greater than 50 mg/day
             Aripiprazole Atomoxetine Beconase Benadryl Benztropine mesylate Bupropion
             Carbamazepine Citalopram Clozapine Coumadin Desipramine-doses greater than 50 mg/day
             Dextroamphetamine Escitalopram Felbamate Fluoxetine Flurazepam Guanethidine
             Guanethidine Haloperidol Hydrocortisone Imipramine-doses greater than 50 mg/day
             Isosorbide dinitrate Kava kava Lamotrigine Lithium Lorazepam Maprotiline-doses
             greater than 50 mg/day Methyldopa Methylphenidate Mifepristone Mirtazapine Modafinil
             Nefazodone Nitroglycerin Nitroprusside Nortriptyline-doses greater than 50 mg/day
             Olanzapine Paroxetine Pemoline Phenelzine Phenylephrine Phenylpropanolamine
             Pramipexole Prednisone Reserpine Risperidone S-adenosyl-methionine (SAME)
             Sinequan-doses greater than 50 mg/day St. John's Wort Tempazepam Testosterone
             injections or patches Tetrahydrozoline Theophylline Tranylcypromine Trazodone
             Valerian Root Valproic acid Warfarin Zalpelon Ziprasidone Zonisamide Zolpidem

          -  Participation in an investigational drug study within 1 month prior to study entry or
             who have received treatment with an investigational drug within 1 month or five
             half-lives, whichever is longer.

          -  Previous investigational study of escitalopram or previously treated with
             escitalopram in a dose and duration sufficient for therapeutic trial.

          -  History of hypersensitivity reaction to escitalopram or citalopram.

          -  Electroconvulsive therapy during the past 3 months

          -  Initiation or termination of behavior therapy or psychotherapy in the 3 months.

          -  Positive urine screening for alcohol, illicit drugs, or any prohibited medication
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>81 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dominique L Musselman, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Grady Hospital Diabetes Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30303</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2008</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 8, 2008</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 14, 2005</firstreceived_date>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Citalopram</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
