<record xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcq="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rownumber="10"><dc:title>Quantifying the Operational Benefits of Conventional and Advanced Pumped Storage Hydro on Reliability and Efficiency: Preprint</dc:title><dc:creator>Krad, I.; Ela, E.; Koritarov, V.</dc:creator><dc:subject>24 POWER TRANSMISSION AND DISTRIBUTION; 13 HYDRO ENERGY AREA CONTROL ERROR (ACE); AUTOMATIC GENERATION CONTROL (AGC); ELECTRICITY MARKETS; PUMPED STORAGE HYDRO (PSH); VARIABLE GENERATION (VG)</dc:subject><dc:subjectRelated>AREA CONTROL ERROR (ACE); AUTOMATIC GENERATION CONTROL (AGC); ELECTRICITY MARKETS; PUMPED STORAGE HYDRO (PSH); VARIABLE GENERATION (VG)</dc:subjectRelated><dc:description>Pumped storage hydro (PSH) plants have significant potential to provide reliability and efficiency benefits in future electric power systems with high penetrations of variable generation. New PSH technologies, such as adjustable-speed PSH, have been introduced that can also present further benefits. This paper demonstrates and quantifies some of the reliability and efficiency benefits afforded by PSH plants by utilizing the Flexible Energy Scheduling Tool for the Integration of Variable generation (FESTIV), an integrated power system operations tool that evaluates both reliability and production costs.</dc:description><dcq:publisher/><dcq:publisherAvailability/><dcq:publisherResearch>National Renewable Energy Laboratory (NREL), Golden, CO.</dcq:publisherResearch><dcq:publisherSponsor>USDOE Office of Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy Water Power Technologies Office</dcq:publisherSponsor><dcq:publisherCountry>United States</dcq:publisherCountry><dc:date>2014-07-01</dc:date><dc:language>English</dc:language><dc:type>Conference</dc:type><dcq:typeQualifier/><dc:relation>Conference: To be presented at the IEEE Power and Energy Society General Meeting, 27-31 July 2014, National Harbor, Maryland</dc:relation><dc:coverage/><dc:format>Medium: ED; Size: 7 pp.</dc:format><dc:identifier>OSTI ID: 1140086, Legacy ID: OSTI ID: 1140086</dc:identifier><dc:identifierReport>NREL/CP-5D00-60806</dc:identifierReport><dcq:identifierDOEcontract>AC36-08GO28308</dcq:identifierDOEcontract><dc:identifierOther/><dc:doi/><dc:rights/><dc:dateEntry>2014-07-21</dc:dateEntry><dc:ostiId>1140086</dc:ostiId><dcq:identifier-purl type="application/pdf">http://www.osti.gov/scitech/servlets/purl/1140086</dcq:identifier-purl><dcq:mediaSequence/></record>