<record xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcq="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rownumber="12"><dc:title>NREL's OpenStudio Helps Design More Efficient Buildings (Fact Sheet)</dc:title><dc:creator>Not Available</dc:creator><dc:subject>32 ENERGY CONSERVATION, CONSUMPTION, AND UTILIZATION; 42 ENGINEERING OPENSTUDIO; DRAG AND DROP; ENERGY EFFICIENCY; EFFICIENT BUILDINGS; ENERGY MODELING; BUILDING DESIGN; SOFTWARE; ENERGYPLUS; RADIANCE; WHOLE BUILDING ENERGY ANALYSIS; DAYLIGHTING PERFORMANCE ANALYSIS; TRIMBLE SKETCHUP; BUILDING COMPONENT LIBRARY; BCL; PARAMETRIC ANALYSIS TOOL; COMPARATIVE ANALYSES; SIMPLE PAYBACK; LIFE-CYCLE COST; SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT; PUBLIC LICENSE; APPLICATION PROGRAMMING INTERFACE</dc:subject><dc:subjectRelated>OPENSTUDIO; DRAG AND DROP; ENERGY EFFICIENCY; EFFICIENT BUILDINGS; ENERGY MODELING; BUILDING DESIGN; SOFTWARE; ENERGYPLUS; RADIANCE; WHOLE BUILDING ENERGY ANALYSIS; DAYLIGHTING PERFORMANCE ANALYSIS; TRIMBLE SKETCHUP; BUILDING COMPONENT LIBRARY; BCL; PARAMETRIC ANALYSIS TOOL; COMPARATIVE ANALYSES; SIMPLE PAYBACK; LIFE-CYCLE COST; SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT; PUBLIC LICENSE; APPLICATION PROGRAMMING INTERFACE</dc:subjectRelated><dc:description>The National Renewable Energy Laboratory (NREL) has created the OpenStudio software platform that makes it easier for architects and engineers to evaluate building energy efficiency measures throughout the design process. OpenStudio makes energy modeling more accessible and affordable, helping professionals to design structures with lower utility bills and less carbon emissions, resulting in a healthier environment. OpenStudio includes a user-friendly application suite that makes the U.S. Department of Energy's EnergyPlus and Radiance simulation engines easier to use for whole building energy and daylighting performance analysis. OpenStudio is freely available and runs on Windows, Mac, and Linux operating systems.</dc:description><dcq:publisher/><dcq:publisherAvailability/><dcq:publisherResearch>National Renewable Energy Laboratory (NREL), Golden, CO.</dcq:publisherResearch><dcq:publisherSponsor>USDOE Office of Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy Communications and Outreach</dcq:publisherSponsor><dcq:publisherCountry>United States</dcq:publisherCountry><dc:date>2014-07-01</dc:date><dc:language>English</dc:language><dc:type>Technical Report</dc:type><dcq:typeQualifier/><dc:relation>Related Information: Innovation Impact: Buildings, NREL (National Renewable Energy Laboratory)</dc:relation><dc:coverage/><dc:format>Medium: ED; Size: 1 pg.</dc:format><dc:identifier>OSTI ID: 1140096, Legacy ID: OSTI ID: 1140096</dc:identifier><dc:identifierReport>NREL/FS-6A42-62338</dc:identifierReport><dcq:identifierDOEcontract>AC36-08GO28308</dcq:identifierDOEcontract><dc:identifierOther/><dc:doi/><dc:rights/><dc:dateEntry>2014-07-21</dc:dateEntry><dc:ostiId>1140096</dc:ostiId><dcq:identifier-purl type="application/pdf">http://www.osti.gov/scitech/servlets/purl/1140096</dcq:identifier-purl><dcq:mediaSequence/></record>